<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 1.6.5
  Last modified: November 24, 2001
  Maintainers: 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Written by Chris Lyttle
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
 <chapter id="chapter7">
 <title>Chapter 7 Investments</title>
 <para>
 This chapter explains how to manage your investments with GnuCash. Most
 people have a investment plan, whether its just putting money into a CD
 account, investing through a company sponsored plan at your workplace or
 buying and selling stocks and bonds through a brokerage. GnuCash gives you
 tools to help you manage these investments such as the <emphasis>Price Editor</emphasis> which allows you to record changes in the prices of stocks you own.
  </para>
 <sect1 id="setupinvest1">
 <title>7.1 Setting Up Accounts (Discussion)</title>
 <para>
 To setup investment accounts in GnuCash you can either use any of the
 predefined categories or setup your own. Investment accounts in GnuCash fall
 into two asset sub-categories, Current Assets and Investments. The Current 
 Assets category is used for the types of accounts that are like savings 
 accounts at your bank such as CD's and Money Market accounts. The Investments
 category is used for the types of accounts where you have a more direct
 ownership stake in the company you are investing in.
 </para>
 <para>
 We discussed previously how you could use a strategy of just setting up
 two accounts to track paying a credit card bill, this simple formula applies
 also here. The minimum you need to do to track investments in GnuCash is to
 setup an account for your brokerage firm or trading account and to add shares
 to it with a price per share and the transfer account that is paying for the
 investment listed in the transfer box. GnuCash will automatically calculate
 the value of the shares and show at the top of the register both the number
 of shares you own and their current value.
 </para>
 <para>
 You can also track each different type of investment individually such as
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
 	Brokerage Accounts
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
	CD's
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
	Treasury Bills
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
	Money Market
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
	Mutual Funds
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
	Stocks
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
	Bonds
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
	Retirements accounts
    </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="createport1">
 <title>7.2 Creating a Portfolio for Your Current Holdings (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 If you used the template account setup back in Chapter's 2 &amp; 3, you will
 see the investment accounts in two places under the Assets category. You can
 use this as a portfolio for your investments or if you wish, create your own
 by creating a new sub-account under Assets.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 In order to receive online price quotes for your stocks you will need to
 setup the Perl module Finance::Quote. This is done by opening a root terminal
 session and typing in 'update-finance-quote' (without the quote marks). This
 will launch a Perl CPAN update session which goes out onto the internet in
 order to install the above module onto your system. If you feel uncomfortable
 about doing this please either email the gnucash-user mailing list
 (gnucash-user@gnucash.org) asking for help or come to the gnucash irc channel
 on irc.gnome.org. You can also leave out this step and manually update your
 stock prices.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 You should now have at least one stock account under the Assets category.
 Select the Assets category:
 insert investaccts.png
 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 Go to the menu and select:
 <menuchoice>
 <guimenu>Account</guimenu>
 <guimenuitem>Open Subaccounts</guimenuitem>
 </menuchoice>
 . This will show you the <emphasis role="strong">Portfolio</emphasis> view.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="buyinvest1">
 <title>7.3 Buying New Investments (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sellinvest1">
 <title>7.4 Selling Investments (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="divint1">
 <title>7.5 Recording Dividends and Interest (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="splitmerge1">
 <title>7.6 Recording Stock Splits and Mergers (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="employeeplan1">
 <title>7.7 Recording Employee Stock Plans (Discussion)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
  <sect2 id="purcstock2">
 <title>7.7.1 Stock Purchase Plans (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="soptions2">
 <title>7.7.2 Stock Options (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="manageport1">
 <title>7.8 Managing your Portfolio (Discussion)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
  <sect2 id="portview2">
 <title>7.8.1  Portfolio View</title>
 <para>
 </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="updateprices2">
 <title>7.8.2 Updating Prices (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="capitalgain2">
 <title>7.8.3 Measuring Capital Gains (Discussion)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="reconcilebroker1">
 <title>7.9 Reconciling with the Brokerage Statement (How-To)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="stockegs1">
 <title>7.10 Putting It All Together (Examples)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 </chapter>
